A Guide to the Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School (Gloucester County, Va.) records, 1877-1929
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School (Gloucester County, Va.) records, 1877-1929
The Library of Virginia
51625a
.955 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School (Gloucester County, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions. The Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School (Gloucester County, Va.) records are part of Weaver Orphan Home records (LVA accession 51625). The rest of the Weaver Orphan Home records are closed until 2065.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Reuben Price, Hampton, Virginia.
Alternative Form Available
Also available as digital images.
Historical Information
Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School was founded in Gloucester County, Virginia, in 1888 by William B. Weaver (1852-1929) and Thomas Calhoun Walker (1862-1953) to educate African Americans. Weaver served as principal and teacher at the school from 1888 to 1899. Originally funded by individual contributions and student tuition, the school received financial support from the American Missionary Association. William Gibbons Price (1868-1941) replaced Weaver as principal in 1899 and served until 1932. Declining student population and the Great Depression led to the school's closing in 1933. At its beginning, the school was known as the Gloucester High School, and through the years it was also known as the Cappahosic School.
Scope and Content
Records, 1877-1929, of the Gloucester Agricultural and Industrial School in Gloucester County, Virginia, founded by Weaver in 1888. Included are articles on the school, catalogues, circulars and forms, correspondence, deeds, programs, and teacher licenses. Of note is a minute and record book containing minutes from the school's formation, as well as invitations and flyers, including to programs where Frederick Douglass was the speaker. There is also a set of the school's monthly newsletter entitled "The Gloucester Messenger," and "The Gloucester Letter," which was written for a short time by Weaver after he severed his ties with the school.
Contents List
- Accounts and Receipts. (Box 41, Folder 1)
- Address to Teachers, 1898. (Box 41, Folder 2)
- American Missionary Association Manual. (Box 41, Folder 3)
- Annual Reports. (Box 41, Folder 4)
- Appeal to American Missionary Association, 1890. (Box 41, Folder 5)
- Article - Advancements of Education for Colored People. (Box 41, Folder 6)
- Article - The Richmond Whig, 1883. (Box 41, Folder 7)
- Article - Southern Workman, May 1893. (Box 41, Folder 8)
- Bethel School. (Box 41, Folder 9)
- Broadsides. (Box 41, Folder 10)
- Bylaws. (Box 41, Folder 11)
- Calendars. (Box 41, Folder 12)
- Cash Accounts, 1894-1896. (Box 41, Folder 13)
- Catalogues. (Box 41, Folder 14)
- Charter. (Box 41, Folder 15)
- Circulars/Forms. (Box 41, Folder 16)
- Clippings. (Box 41, Folder 17)
- Correspondence. (Box 41, Folder 18)
- Deeds. (Box 41, Folder 19)
- Educational Conference and Tenth Anniversary Exercises, 1898. (Box 41, Folder 20)
- Examination of Teachers, 1877. (Box 41, Folder 21)
- The Gloucester Letter, 1888-1900. (Box 42, Folder 1-13)
- The Gloucester Messenger, 1899-1900. (Box 42, Folder 14-15)
- Invitations. (Box 42, Folder 16)
- Letter to Board of Trustees, 9 October 1890. (Box 42, Folder 17)
- Letters of Introduction/Support (Box 42, Folder 18)
- Minute and Record Book (Box 56, Folder n/a)
- Minutes (Box 42, Folder 19)
- The News (Hampton, VA), 16 July 1881. (Box 42, Folder 20)
- Photograph - Weaver Residence, Cappahosic, VA (Box 42, Folder 21)
- Plat, 1885 (Box 42, Folder 22)
- Programs (Box 42, Folder 23)
- "A Rural School Builder" by Lizzie Baytop Baker, 1929 (Box 42, Folder 24)
- Sale of Cappahosic Land, 1903 (Box 42, Folder 25)
- School Exercises (Box 42, Folder 26)
- Scrapbook of Estelle I. Sprague (Frederick Douglass Clippings), 1896. (Volume 10)
- The Sunday School Missionary, April 1884. (Box 42, Folder 27)
- Taxes. (Box 42, Folder 28)
- Teacher's Licenses. (Box 42, Folder 29)
- The Tract Repository. (Box 42, Folder 30)